<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>dataaa.net</title><description>Technical musings of Paul Woods</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.7</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 22:34:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>10 points to Gryffindor!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;A brief hiatus here on the blog whilst I relocated to the best city in the world, London. To blow off some cobwebs, I flexed my Python/Matplotlib muscles and took a look at the Harry Potter books by J.K. Rowling. Parsing the text of the books, I extracted&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/10-points-to-gryffindor/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">019462c6-0a81-43fa-92ab-905a3a86e684</guid><category>Harry Potter</category><category>Gryffindor</category><category>JK Rowling</category><category>Quidditch</category><category>house points</category><category>Slytherin</category><category>Ravenclaw</category><category>Hufflepuff</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 17:39:27 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/03/HarryPotterPoints-1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/03/HarryPotterPoints-1.png" alt="10 points to Gryffindor!"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A brief hiatus here on the blog whilst I relocated to the best city in the world, London. To blow off some cobwebs, I flexed my Python/Matplotlib muscles and took a look at the Harry Potter books by J.K. Rowling. Parsing the text of the books, I extracted the awards of house points by various Hogwarts teachers, and here they are! &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2016/03/HarryPotterPoints.png" alt="10 points to Gryffindor!"&gt;
Unfortunately there is not a complete record of points awarded in the books... in a rare instance, the final totals are given at the end of &lt;strong&gt;Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone&lt;/strong&gt;: Gryffindor 482 pts, Slytherin 472 pts, Ravenclaw 426 pts, Hufflepuff 352 pts. This shows that we're missing the award of 469 points to Gryffindor and huge numbers of points for the other houses. Clearly we're missing many of the points awarded through Quidditch victories, but there must be multiple other gains and losses which Rowling, understandably, does not bother to cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which pupils are the most rewarded, and which are the biggest liabilities? Look below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class="tg"&gt;  
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Pupil&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Awarded&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Forfeited&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Ron Weasley&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;305&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;103.33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;201.67&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;350&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;265.33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;84.67&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Hermione Granger&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;195&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;80&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Neville Longbottom&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;80&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;53.33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;26.67&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;Draco Malfoy&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class="tg-yw4l"&gt;-20&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Cameron, we don't believe you</title><description>&lt;p&gt;It has only been six months since the last General Election in the UK, but already a proportion of the UK population are losing faith in their Prime Minister, David Cameron. The ruling Conservative party have been coming under fire in the media after &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/yvette-cooper/election-promises-broken_b_7949232.html"&gt;broken election promises&lt;/a&gt;, post-election U-turns and&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/cameron-we-dont-believe-you/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">4bf704a7-9dac-4a62-a5e7-fd761846ee69</guid><category>maps</category><category>politics</category><category>David Cameron</category><category>petition</category><category>no confidence</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 12:57:40 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/11/cameronOut-1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/11/cameronOut-1.png" alt="Cameron, we don't believe you"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has only been six months since the last General Election in the UK, but already a proportion of the UK population are losing faith in their Prime Minister, David Cameron. The ruling Conservative party have been coming under fire in the media after &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/yvette-cooper/election-promises-broken_b_7949232.html"&gt;broken election promises&lt;/a&gt;, post-election U-turns and their aggressive pro-austerity policies. I recently noted &lt;a href="https://petition.parliament.uk/petitions/104471"&gt;a petition, asking the House of Commons to debate having a vote of 'no confidence' in David Cameron&lt;/a&gt;. At the time of writing, it has amassed nearly 170,000 signatories, and that list seems to be growing at a rate of thousands per day. And there are still two months left to run. 170,000 votes is nothing compared to the turnout for the General Election 2015 (some 45 million people), but it will be interesting to see how many votes this government petition will result in. At 100,000 signatories, the government must consider any petition seriously, possibly even tabling it for debate within the House of Commons. So this action will clearly get some attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/11/cameronOut.png" alt="Cameron, we don't believe you"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most disillusioned constituency (not shown on this map, since it is a clear outlier) is, ironically, the City of Westminster, with nearly 6,500 votes of 'No confidence'. It is not clear, however, how many addresses entered onto the petition are genuine. Other areas of the country with visible lack of confidence in the Prime Minister are Teeside, the West Country and the South-West, the west Wales coast, the Highlands of Scotland and the northern industrial cities of Manchester, Liverpool, Blackpool and Preston.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The highways &amp; byways of Belfast</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/08/mmrBelfast.png" alt="Map of Belfast defined by its runners"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map above shows some of the roads of Belfast, but as defined by the footsteps of its inhabitants. I have plotted over 3,000 running and walking routes as registered by users of the MapMyRun website. The more opaque the line, the more well-trodden the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This visualisation uses&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/the-highways-byways-of-belfast/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">454b65a1-0048-4bd8-b572-ea77cf729a9f</guid><category>maps</category><category>Belfast</category><category>GPS</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 21:12:52 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/08/mmrBelfast-1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/08/mmrBelfast-1.png" alt="The highways &amp; byways of Belfast"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/08/mmrBelfast.png" alt="The highways &amp; byways of Belfast"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map above shows some of the roads of Belfast, but as defined by the footsteps of its inhabitants. I have plotted over 3,000 running and walking routes as registered by users of the MapMyRun website. The more opaque the line, the more well-trodden the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This visualisation uses GPS tracks from wearables or routes manually input via the MapMyRun website. Obtaining these GPS tracks (as .gpx files) can be tricky, but UnderArmour, recent owners of the MapMyRun/Ride/Walk/Hike/Fitness franchise have a &lt;a href="https://developer.underarmour.com"&gt;very generous API&lt;/a&gt;, which allows 100,000 calls per day (and up to 25 per second). It is possible to get a list of routes in a particular region via an API call, but it is equally straightforward enough to just parse an HTML list: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;http://www.mapmyrun.com/gb/belfast-nir/routes&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Each page is limited to 1,000 routes, but can be iterated through using &lt;code&gt;limit&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;offset&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;http://www.mapmyrun.com/gb/belfast-nir/routes?limit=3000&amp;amp;offset=2000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GPX files (which are basically a list of longitude and latitude points) can be accessed via the UA API: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;https://oauth2-api.mapmyapi.com/v7.1/route/&amp;lt;route number&amp;gt;/?field_set=detailed&amp;amp;format=gpx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The API requires certain headers to be sent, which can be achieved with the &lt;code&gt;httr::GET&lt;/code&gt; command in &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;add_headers&lt;/code&gt; option. However, a complexity of the &lt;code&gt;httr::GET&lt;/code&gt; command is that data is stored in memory (in binary form), and therefore must be written to disk in order to be used. Thus the full call is something along the lines of: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;GET(paste0(fileUrl1,route_id,fileUrl2),add_headers("api-key" = &amp;lt;my_api_key&amp;gt;, "authorization" = "&amp;lt;my_secret_key&amp;gt;"), accept("application/gpx+xml"), write_disk(paste0("MapMyRun_", route_id, ".gpx")), progress())&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the GPX files are obtained, the longitude and latitude points from each route can be stored in a data frame, and plotted with &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; or similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shapefile used to give the background layer is courtesy of NISRA and subject to Crown Copyright.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Police deaths in the UK (another approach)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;After yesterday's discovery that &lt;a href="http://dataaa.github.io/police-deaths-in-the-uk/"&gt;the adjusted rate of deaths following contact with the England &amp;amp; Wales police forces was higher than that in the US&lt;/a&gt;, I set out to try to verify this information. As I stated yesterday, there is no systematic, reliable record of deaths caused by the police&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/police-deaths-in-the-uk-another-approach/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">4f59302f-695c-45b5-9885-14111e41da72</guid><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 15:43:50 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;After yesterday's discovery that &lt;a href="http://dataaa.github.io/police-deaths-in-the-uk/"&gt;the adjusted rate of deaths following contact with the England &amp;amp; Wales police forces was higher than that in the US&lt;/a&gt;, I set out to try to verify this information. As I stated yesterday, there is no systematic, reliable record of deaths caused by the police in the USA, and any attempts to start such a record have not been supported by individual police departments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a website called &lt;a href="http://www.killedbypolice.net"&gt;www.killedbypolice.net&lt;/a&gt;, where some diligent person or persons have been recording police-caused deaths since 1 May 2013. Each reported death is backed up by a link to a media website. After much wrangling (much messy HTML!) I extracted this information using &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; and plotted it with my previous data, this time just for the period from 1 May 2013 until today (normalising as necessary). &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/policeScaledDeathRateNoSuic2-1.png" alt=""&gt;
This view paints a different picture: it shows that the death rate for English &amp;amp; Welsh police is similar to that reported on Wikipedia for US police. It also shows that there are more than twice as many killings reported on killedbypolice.net as on Wikipedia. 4.6 more people per million have been killed by US police compared to UK police, over the last two years, and &lt;em&gt;you are more than three times as likely to be killed by a police officer in the US than in the UK&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Police deaths in the UK (updated)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;If you've been following this blog at all, you'll know that I've been watching with interest &lt;a href="http://dataaa.github.io/police-killings-in-the-usa/"&gt;the series of police-related deaths in the USA&lt;/a&gt;. The rate of these deaths (to be precise, the rate of reported deaths: this may be increasing as awareness increases) &lt;a href="http://dataaa.github.io/police-killings-in-the-usa-pt-2/"&gt;seems to be increasing dramatically&lt;/a&gt;. Two&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/police-deaths-in-the-uk/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">4ff0fa9a-79a6-463d-a172-e5ba1768f467</guid><category>data</category><category>police killings</category><category>UK</category><category>USA</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 10:34:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;If you've been following this blog at all, you'll know that I've been watching with interest &lt;a href="http://dataaa.github.io/police-killings-in-the-usa/"&gt;the series of police-related deaths in the USA&lt;/a&gt;. The rate of these deaths (to be precise, the rate of reported deaths: this may be increasing as awareness increases) &lt;a href="http://dataaa.github.io/police-killings-in-the-usa-pt-2/"&gt;seems to be increasing dramatically&lt;/a&gt;. Two more high-profile cases hit the news this week: the reported suicides of activists &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/newsbeat/article/33649861/sandra-blands-death-in-us-custody-seven-questions-about-what-happened"&gt;Sandra Bland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.bustle.com/articles/99920-what-happened-to-rexdale-henry-a-native-american-activist-his-death-is-drawing-comparisons-to-sandra"&gt;Rexdale Henry&lt;/a&gt; whilst in police custody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week the Independent Police Complaints Commission in the UK &lt;a href="https://www.ipcc.gov.uk/page/deaths-during-or-following-police-contact"&gt;released its figures for deaths during or following police contact&lt;/a&gt;  for the year.  These data give, amongst other things, deaths related to police vehicle pursuits, police shootings, deaths in custody, and suicides within 2 days of release from police custody for police forces in England and Wales. There were 142 deaths in 2014/2015, including one shooting. In the plot below I have summarised the last 10 years' worth of data. It is good to see that the number of deaths per year is holding steady at around the 140 mark, if not decreasing slightly. These figures are independently assembled, and thoroughly investigated, and therefore should be accurate. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/policeUK.png" alt="Police-related deaths in England and Wales"&gt;
Whilst many categories show a decreasing rate of deaths (Road Traffic Incidents, Shootings, Custody Incidents), suicides have been increasing at a rate of approx. 2 per year, which goes to show the increasing pressure the police force is under to deal with and understand mental health issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the England &amp;amp; Wales rate (which I will erroneously call the 'UK' rate from now on) differ from the death rate in the US? &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_killings_by_law_enforcement_officers_in_the_United_States"&gt;It is hard to find figures for the US that are as stringent as those from the IPCC&lt;/a&gt;, and so as a surrogate I will use the reported deaths from the log on Wikipedia. Note (well) that these are reported deaths, often from media sources, they are not official police figures. However, a recent study in Florida found that &lt;strong&gt;local media reported four times as many police deaths as local police did&lt;/strong&gt;. It would be senseless to compare death totals in the 'UK' and the US without scaling for population (there is a factor ~5 difference), so I have plotted deaths per million since 2009, below: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/policeScaledDeathRate.png" alt="Comparative police-related deaths in the UK and US"&gt;
The difference is marked: almost twice as many police-related deaths per million in the UK as in the US, since 2009. It is clear that the data collected from Wikipedia is not as rigorous as the IPCC data, and therefore we might expect the Wikipedia data to provide a lower limit to US death counts. From browsing the Wikipedia list entries, it is also clear that they focus on directly-caused deaths, and often deaths from violence (shootings, beatings), whereas the IPCC data include, for instance, suicides that have occurred outside of police custody, which may however have been significantly influenced by contact with the police. If we exclude the 'suicide' category from the IPCC data, the two counts become more comparable: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/policeScaledDeathRateNoSuic.png" alt="Comparative police-related deaths in the UK and US, excluding UK suicides"&gt;
Without more complete data from the US it is hard to say whether there is a significant difference here, but it is at least interesting and surprising to see that the 'UK' rate is so high in comparison to that in the US. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Empty homes in London</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Living in London is, for many and especially Dick Whittington, a dream. But it's a dream that comes with a hefty price tag: average monthly rental prices are nearly £1,500, compared to a national average of £750 or so. Despite this, the population of London continues to grow by&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/empty-homes-in-london/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">54e86182-9335-492f-8ac0-8932a1eec56d</guid><category>data</category><category>maps</category><category>London</category><category>vacant buildings</category><category>housing</category><category>demographics</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2015 11:25:14 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Living in London is, for many and especially Dick Whittington, a dream. But it's a dream that comes with a hefty price tag: average monthly rental prices are nearly £1,500, compared to a national average of £750 or so. Despite this, the population of London continues to grow by approx. 1.3% per year, and is now at around 8.6M people (Greater London), levels which haven't been seen since the middle of the last century (Second World War). Given that the number of houses built in all of England last year was about 120,000, the pressure on fitting more people into existing structures in London is increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homelessness is also increasing, up 7% in London from 2013 to 2014. This brings the estimated total to about 750 people, almost a quarter of the homeless people in England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these pressures, councils in London are turning their attention to vacant buildings, and developing strategies for populating them where possible. It seems to be working. I pulled some data on vacant buildings from the London Datastore, and put together this animated visualisation in an attractive "rhubarb and custard" colour scheme: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/londonVac.gif" alt="Vacant buildings in London, 2004-2013"&gt;
(Mapping data contains National Statistics data © Crown copyright and database right [2015] and Ordnance Survey data © Crown copyright and database right [2015]. Map shows number of vacant buildings per hectare.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exception of Kensington &amp;amp; Chelsea, which is the most expensive place to live in London (renters here can expect to pay in excess of £3,100 per month) most boroughs are reducing their vacant premises significantly, especially since 2008, when mayor Boris Johnston came into office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The animation also shows the regeneration of some places like Hackney over the last 10 years or so. Hackney was once something of an industrial wasteland, but is now becoming one of the more trendy London boroughs to live in. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The London skyline</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I went to London. It used to be my home, and one of the things that I realised I missed about London when I went back there was the London skyline. There's very little like it anywhere in the world (okay, New York perhaps...) and it's &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; impressive.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/the-london-skyline/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e87637b4-cb3c-452d-b086-3b168ab22f59</guid><category>maps</category><category>London</category><category>buildings</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 12:31:38 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/IMG_4746.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/IMG_4746.JPG" alt="The London skyline"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I went to London. It used to be my home, and one of the things that I realised I missed about London when I went back there was the London skyline. There's very little like it anywhere in the world (okay, New York perhaps...) and it's &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this trip I took the opportunity to go up to level 33 of the Shard. This was not even half the way up the tallest building in London (73 floors, 306m), but it still offered breathtaking views across the capital. This past week I tried to get hold of a dataset offering the heights of buildings in London. It's tricky. There's a very expensive but also very extensive dataset from Ordnance Survey. But then eventually I found a website from Emporis which housed a list of heights for about 2,000 buildings in London: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.emporis.com/city/100637/london-united-kingdom"&gt;http://www.emporis.com/city/100637/london-united-kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was little trouble to scrape these webpages using the excellent &lt;code&gt;readHTMLTable&lt;/code&gt; function in the &lt;code&gt;XML&lt;/code&gt; package in R. After a touch of data cleaning and wrangling (Google couldn't automatically geocode about 40 of these buildings) I put together a few plots showing the London skyline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/londonMapTallBuildings.png" alt="The London skyline"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second plot is from the south of London, looking north. I have colour-coded the points so that the red points are buildings built pre-Second World War, and green points post-Second World War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/londonSkyline.png" alt="The London skyline"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prize for the person who can name the tall building near Chessington...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The trees of Belfast</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I can't show you the results of the data analysis I performed at the &lt;a href="http://www.dataaa.net/urban-data-hackathon"&gt;Urban Data Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; (see previous post) due to a non-disclosure agreement, but I can show you a visualisation I made with one of Belfast City Council's open datasets: &lt;a href="http://www.belfastcity.gov.uk/council/Openandlinkeddata/opendatasets.aspx"&gt;their street trees dataset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/koreana/299010049/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/trees-of-belfast/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ebfe8aba-9d83-4ff4-b29b-32448c09cc06</guid><category>data</category><category>maps</category><category>Belfast</category><category>trees</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 09:48:42 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I can't show you the results of the data analysis I performed at the &lt;a href="http://www.dataaa.net/urban-data-hackathon"&gt;Urban Data Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; (see previous post) due to a non-disclosure agreement, but I can show you a visualisation I made with one of Belfast City Council's open datasets: &lt;a href="http://www.belfastcity.gov.uk/council/Openandlinkeddata/opendatasets.aspx"&gt;their street trees dataset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/koreana/299010049/"&gt;a CC BY-SA 2.0 image of a heart&lt;/a&gt;, I made this map of Belfast. Note that this only shows &lt;em&gt;street trees&lt;/em&gt; and so many of Belfast's parks are not represented. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/belfasttrees-poster.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Urban Data Hackathon</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I was fortunate enough to be one of 40 or so people to attend &lt;a href="http://www.beltech2015.com/hackathon/"&gt;Belfast's "Urban Data Hackathon"&lt;/a&gt; weekend. Organised as part of Belfast's Big Data Week by Kainos Software, and supported with data from Belfast City Council, TomTom, TourismNI and various others, it challenged people to dig&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/urban-data-hackathon/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">d7c6f6e1-5346-441e-b5f8-b33283e90e8a</guid><category>data</category><category>Belfast</category><category>review</category><category>hackathon</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 08:26:04 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/UDH15-logo.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/07/UDH15-logo.jpg" alt="Urban Data Hackathon"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I was fortunate enough to be one of 40 or so people to attend &lt;a href="http://www.beltech2015.com/hackathon/"&gt;Belfast's "Urban Data Hackathon"&lt;/a&gt; weekend. Organised as part of Belfast's Big Data Week by Kainos Software, and supported with data from Belfast City Council, TomTom, TourismNI and various others, it challenged people to dig into some open and proprietary datasets to learn more about Belfast and to "Make Belfast Better".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We split into teams, and formulated questions to answer with the data we had been provided: a variety of information about recycling, events and vacant storefronts from Belfast City Council, Twitter stream analytics from TourismNI, route data from TomTom and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;24 hours later, we presented our findings to a panel of judges, who picked a winner: a team which took data on household recycling in Belfast and came up with an idea to turn recycling into a competition, pitting one area of Belfast against another in a recycling war, for the glory of winning a gold badge for their area. Their idea of trying to motivate people to recycle was appreciated by the judges, although they did not use the data in any significant way. The second placed team also looked at the recycling data, but really dug into what was available, and pulled in other data resources (census information, weather) to try to understand the factors involved in recycling yield. There was not enough time to really produce a decent model, but their initial attempt found some minor correlations with different factors such as religion, gender, and whether or not you were German (Germans in Belfast tend not to produce much recyclable material, apparently...!). The third placed team looked at the position of vacant lots in Belfast city centre, and suggested using the vacant lots for start-up companies. They identified 44 'prime' lots that could be used for this purpose, but apart from that, did not really dig into the data or offer a viable solution in terms of cost effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so the weekend was a mixed bag, with some teams doing some excellent data analysis and not being rewarded for it, and other teams being very cursory in their data analysis but having good business ideas. It opened my eyes a little to the business side of data which I had not fully considered before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chosen project for the weekend was to analyse Twitter stream analytics for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/discoverni"&gt;the @DiscoverNI Twitter account&lt;/a&gt;. Using the permalinks for all the tweets from the past year, I identified what I called @DiscoverNI's "Twitter Champions"... those followers of @DiscoverNI with a large following themselves who retweeted @DiscoverNI's content to their own audience. By identifying the most influential of these people, I suggested that they could be targeted and encouraged to continue sharing @DiscoverNI content through invitations, discounted tickets, etc. to @DiscoverNI events throughout the year. I did all the scripting in &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;, and was continually frustrated by the frequency and volume limitations on the Twitter API...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, a good weekend with some interesting people and some fun challenges. The staff at Kainos did a great job of organising and facilitating the 'hackers'. Hopefully there will be more of these events to come in the future!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Belfast Bikes!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The Belfast Bike scheme launched in Belfast at the end of April 2015, in a similar setup to London's "Boris Bike" scheme: you can rent bicycles for short periods of time for small amounts of money, picking them up and dropping them off as needed at docking points around the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/belfast-bikes/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2c937547-e7d8-478e-aa95-6a7de0745a20</guid><category>data</category><category>maps</category><category>northern ireland</category><category>Belfast</category><category>bike share</category><category>Belfast Bikes</category><category>bike</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 21:16:42 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/06/IMG_3969.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/06/IMG_3969.JPG" alt="Belfast Bikes!"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Belfast Bike scheme launched in Belfast at the end of April 2015, in a similar setup to London's "Boris Bike" scheme: you can rent bicycles for short periods of time for small amounts of money, picking them up and dropping them off as needed at docking points around the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Belfast scheme is run by a company called Nextbike, which is a German company that runs these city bike schemes mostly in Eastern Europe. Unfortunately they do not make their bike rental data public in any very useful fashion. Some beautiful stuff has been done with bikeshare data, for example &lt;a href="http://oobrien.com/2014/09/from-putney-to-poplar-12-million-journeys-on-the-london-bikeshare/"&gt;this dendritic map of London is the result of plotting millions of cycle journeys&lt;/a&gt;. However, Nextbike only make available an XML feed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;https://nextbike.net/maps/nextbike-live.xml?city=238
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feed updates every 10 minutes, and shows the number of bikes in each dock if there are less than 5. If there are 5 or more, it simply states that there are '5+' bikes, rather unhelpfully, despite some docking stations having spaces for up to 24 bikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed this XML feed for a few days to produce the following animated graphic. I was hoping to see a rather wonderful ebb and flow of bikes into the city during the morning and out of the city in the evenings, but the limited data products from the scheme, and also the fact that docking stations are often over-full (hopefully just early teething problems as the scheme finds its feet) mean that there is little temporal variation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/06/belfastBikeFlow.gif" alt="Belfast Bikes!"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue for measuring the diurnal ebb and flow is that the extent of the scheme is restricted to the centre of the city: none of the bike stations are in suburban areas. Even the most southerly docking stations only make it to the very northern reaches of the student areas of the city, implying that this bike scheme is squarely aimed at the tourist, not at making the city more well connected for the residents or improving overall health... at least at this point in time. Belfast City Council say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Belfast Bikes are used by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;residents: to travel to work, go shopping, go somewhere different for lunch or visit friends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tourists: to visit the city's attractions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;students: as a cheap and easy way to travel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commuters: to cycle to and from the bus stop, car park or train station to their workplaces"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase 1A of the scheme will hopefully tackle the student aspect of this vision: more docking stations are planned to be planted at the Queen's Students' Union and campus. Phase 2, currently in the planning stages, will target commuting residents, with docking points in the west and east of the city.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Police killings in the USA (pt. 2)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;After a spate of new killings at the hands of law enforcement officials in the USA, particularly deaths that have occurred in police custody (notably those of Freddie Gray and David Dehmann) and after collisions with police vehicles, I wanted to look at whether the rate of deaths had increased&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/police-killings-in-the-usa-pt-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e3debe48-f2c8-4766-aedc-e85ab814d517</guid><category>web</category><category>data</category><category>R</category><category>police killings</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 07:50:20 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;After a spate of new killings at the hands of law enforcement officials in the USA, particularly deaths that have occurred in police custody (notably those of Freddie Gray and David Dehmann) and after collisions with police vehicles, I wanted to look at whether the rate of deaths had increased recently. Using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_killings_by_law_enforcement_officers_in_the_United_States"&gt;data from Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, and using &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; to scrape and process the data, I plotted the reported deaths over the last six years or so: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/05/policeDeathRate.png" alt=""&gt;
Note that these are &lt;em&gt;reported&lt;/em&gt; deaths, and thus the data may not be complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that the rate of reported deaths due to law enforcement officials in the US has increased dramatically, particularly in the last year or so. From the graph, three pickups in rate seem evident, in February 2010, June 2012 and August 2014. The most recent spike in numbers is particularly surprising, since the death of Michael Brown at the start of this period led directly to widespread public protests in Ferguson, Missouri, and across the country. Rather than curb police brutality, it seems to have continued at a steady (but elevated) rate for several months subsequently. During this period Tamir Rice was also shot and killed, leading to further protests in Cleveland. And only last month, Freddie Gray was killed in police custody in Baltimore, leading to prolonged protests and enforced curfews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that people in authority are starting to take notice. The US Justice Department &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-32632516"&gt;is now probing the behaviour of Baltimore Police&lt;/a&gt; and the UN Human Rights Council is &lt;a href="http://america.aljazeera.com/articles/2015/5/11/us-faces-scathing-un-review-on-human-rights-record.html"&gt;making its concerns known&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The security situation in Northern Ireland</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Northern_Ireland"&gt;history of Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; has been troubled for many many years, with the most recent eruption of violence (&lt;em&gt;"The Troubles"&lt;/em&gt;) spanning from the late 1960s until a political ceasefire was called in 1998. In 2005, only 10 years ago, the main paramilitary group involved in The Troubles, the IRA&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/security-situation-in-northern-ireland/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5862de70-f665-46aa-85c5-029505bbbb8f</guid><category>data</category><category>maps</category><category>R</category><category>northern ireland</category><category>security situation</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 07:57:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Northern_Ireland"&gt;history of Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; has been troubled for many many years, with the most recent eruption of violence (&lt;em&gt;"The Troubles"&lt;/em&gt;) spanning from the late 1960s until a political ceasefire was called in 1998. In 2005, only 10 years ago, the main paramilitary group involved in The Troubles, the IRA (aligned with the Republican movement) declared a disarmament, and a resolution to pursue purely political means of restitution. However, it is clear from the current situation in the province that the past has not been forgotten, and the animosity between the Unionists (who are in favour of NI being part of the UK) and the Republicans (Irish Nationalists, against the union with the UK) is still alive and well, and is being cultivated by the respective factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Police Service of Northern Ireland (PSNI) keep a record of incidents that they attribute to the so-called "security situation", which shows that although paramilitary-style killings are now very low, other incidents, such as shootings, bombings, uses of incendaries, and assaults, occur on a regular basis. These incidents are routinely assigned to either loyalist (Unionist) or republican (Nationalist) groups, and often reported in the press to be due to 'dissident' elements in both camps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PSNI today published their data for 2014/15. I took a look at it, and saw that the north and west of Belfast, and the region of Foyle (which contains the city (London)Derry) are still battlegrounds for what is essentially gang warfare. I looked at shootings, punishment assaults/shootings (inflicted by a sect upon its own members) and bomb/incendiary useage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/05/1415-Shootings-1.png" alt="Paramilitary shootings in Northern Ireland"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/05/1415-Assaults-2.png" alt="Paramilitary punishments in Northern Ireland"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/05/1415-Bombings-1.png" alt="Paramilitary bombings in Northern Ireland"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.psni.police.uk/index/updates/updates_statistics/updates_security_situation_statistics.htm"&gt;Data from PSNI Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on this to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Police killings in the USA</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently there have been a number of high-profile cases in the media of law-enforcement officials throughout the USA killing unarmed citizens. Whether this be &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-32212958"&gt;the shooting in the back of someone stopped for a traffic violation&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-30317807"&gt;the choking to death of someone selling untaxed cigarettes on the street&lt;/a&gt;, people&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/police-killings-in-the-usa/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">32a5b361-afaf-432b-b7db-e0ec4f27dd3e</guid><category>maps</category><category>R</category><category>police killings</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 15:59:39 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Recently there have been a number of high-profile cases in the media of law-enforcement officials throughout the USA killing unarmed citizens. Whether this be &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-32212958"&gt;the shooting in the back of someone stopped for a traffic violation&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-30317807"&gt;the choking to death of someone selling untaxed cigarettes on the street&lt;/a&gt;, people are dying at the hands of a police force that pledges to serve and to protect its citizens. The most recent case is &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-32406219"&gt;that of a man who was detained by the police, and whilst in custody, he developed life-threatening and ultimately fatal spinal injuries&lt;/a&gt;. The implication is that he suffered police brutality, resulting in his death. The most impactful of these killings in recent times was &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-28841715"&gt;that of Michael Brown in Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt;. That event alone sparked weeks of protests in the southern USA, and country-wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes these incidents more controversial, perhaps, is the fact that the deceased are often poor, sometimes homeless, often unarmed, often of African-American ethnicity and for me, the most insidious thing is that the police officers involved have a Get-Out-Of-Jail-Free card... they just have to allege that the victim in some way reached for the officer's own taser or sidearm. Even if that is not the case. The shooting of Walter Cross, the traffic violator mentioned above, was captured in video footage. Despite the police officer's recounting of the situation, Mr. Cross did not appear to reach for any weapons. Unsubstantiated footage from Reddit &lt;a href="http://redd.it/31yp9t"&gt;allegedly shows a police officer dropping a taser next to the deceased body of Walter Cross&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to investigate how widespread these police-induced deaths have been in recent years. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_killings_by_law_enforcement_officers_in_the_United_States"&gt;Thankfully there is a list of incidents on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;. Since 2009 until the present day, there have been over 2,000. Of course, not all of the deaths are reported or collated, and not all of them are 'unlawful', but that gives some idea of the scale of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;, I scraped the data and plotted it on a map of the USA. The problem is widespread, from coast to coast. At present, the mapped distribution is affected by population density: there are more killings in populated areas, simply because there are more people, and more police. In future weeks I will produce a choropleth map, showing the relative density of these incidents across the states of the USA. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/04/2015killings.png" alt="Police killings in the USA"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>What's the most popular gear amongst professional photographers?</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.shotkit.com"&gt;Shotkit.com&lt;/a&gt; is a website which opens up professional photographers' camera bags to show what equipment they use in their working lives. This is interesting not only to gear-heads, but also to average photographers who are looking for a better tool for the job, or to upgrade a piece of&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/whats-the-most-popular-gear-amongst-professional-photographers/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f62e5333-341a-44bf-a006-1dd437bed0d3</guid><category>web</category><category>data</category><category>photography</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 16:09:19 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/03/allGear.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/03/allGear.png" alt="What's the most popular gear amongst professional photographers?"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.shotkit.com"&gt;Shotkit.com&lt;/a&gt; is a website which opens up professional photographers' camera bags to show what equipment they use in their working lives. This is interesting not only to gear-heads, but also to average photographers who are looking for a better tool for the job, or to upgrade a piece of equipment. Each page on Shotkit.com contains an interview with a photographer, and usually a beautifully-shot photo of their camera bag contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about what kind of equipment professional photographers used, and it struck me that Shotkit.com was a great repository of the latest and greatest gear. So I set about collating the information on the site, and putting together a few interesting graphics. Using a script written in &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;, I looked at different genres of photography and plotted the most popular gear for each genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="weddingphotography"&gt;Wedding photography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/03/Wedding.png" alt="What's the most popular gear amongst professional photographers?"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The professional wedding photography market is dominated by Canon, and particularly by its all-round winner of a DSLR, the Canon 5D mark III. To pair with this great camera body, pro photographers opt for a range of Canon prime lenses: 24mm f/1.4L, 35mm f/1.4L, 50mm f/1.2L, 85mm f/1.2L and the 135 f/2L. What an amazing lineup of lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikon camera bodies lag surprisingly behind the pocketable point'n'shoot, the Fuji X100S. The Nikon D3S and D700, although excellent cameras, are veritably ancient in the fast-paced camera market. Nikon's latest additions, the D800, D810 and D750, don't show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special mentions should be given to a very popular gadget, the &lt;a href="http://holdfastgear.com/products/money-maker-luxury-leather-multi-camera-strap"&gt;Holdfast Money Maker&lt;/a&gt;, which is a high-grade leather camera strap (priced at $200+), and a lens from a third-party manufacturer, the Sigma 35mm f/1.4 Art lens, which by all accounts is an excellent ensemble of glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="landscapephotographers"&gt;Landscape photographers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portrait, travel and commerical photographers also favour Canon equipment, whereas Sports photographers are more evenly spread in Canon and Nikon camps. Fashion photographers tend to favour the high resolution of the Nikon D800.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the most used piece of equipment amongst professional landscape photographers is not a camera or lens at all... it's a graduated filter, which equalises the exposure in the frame between a bright sky and not-so-bright landscape: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/03/Landscape.png" alt="What's the most popular gear amongst professional photographers?"&gt;
Also here we see the first appearance of a Sony camera, and again a good third-party lens, the Samyang 14mm f/2.8, which excels at astrophotography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2015/03/allGear-1.png" alt="What's the most popular gear amongst professional photographers?"&gt;
Overall, the Canon dominance over the professional photographers of Shotkit.com is complete. The 5D Mark III body, partnered with Canon's L series lenses, outweighs the competition in the sample more than 2-to-1. Nikon's most popular offering is the D800 camera, with the excellent 24-70mm f/2.8 and 70-200mm f/2.8 lenses. Adobe Lightroom is the most popular software, more so than long-time favourite Adobe Photoshop.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Welcome to Ghost + Buster</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been looking for a blogging platform that looks great, is easy to use, and can be self-hosted. Some new kids on the block (I'm looking at you &lt;a href="https://www.medium.com"&gt;medium&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.svbtle.com"&gt;svbtle&lt;/a&gt;) look fabulous but aren't self-hosted, and others (&lt;a href="https://www.jekyllrb.com"&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt;) are, but are very complicated to get going&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/welcome-to-ghost/#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;a href="https://www.ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; seems&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/welcome-to-ghost/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">753e2dbd-724f-4f38-8c45-7625177d7313</guid><category>web</category><category>blog</category><dc:creator>Paul W</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 15:44:06 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I've been looking for a blogging platform that looks great, is easy to use, and can be self-hosted. Some new kids on the block (I'm looking at you &lt;a href="https://www.medium.com"&gt;medium&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.svbtle.com"&gt;svbtle&lt;/a&gt;) look fabulous but aren't self-hosted, and others (&lt;a href="https://www.jekyllrb.com"&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt;) are, but are very complicated to get going&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/welcome-to-ghost/#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;a href="https://www.ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; seems to fill the gap: it is lightweight, has a nice post creation portal (as opposed to Jekyll), can be hosted on Github, and has a ton of &lt;a href="https://marketplace.ghost.org/"&gt;good-looking themes&lt;/a&gt; that are mostly available for free. Above all, it is easy to get set up! There is a &lt;a href="https://xavierriley.co.uk/blogging-with-ghost-buster-and-github-pages/index.html"&gt;very good post by Xavier Riley&lt;/a&gt; which helps immensely. I'm sure there will be problems to come (perhaps with installing updates to Ghost and/or themes), but so far so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost partners with Buster, a static site generator which makes it very easy to 'deploy' a site to Github Pages. Once Ghost and Buster and their dependencies are installed and set up (see above link), the workflow is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; npm start --production&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
(starts a local Node server)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browse to &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/ghost"&gt;http://localhost:2368/ghost&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; log in&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Write post&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; buster generate --domain=http://localhost:2368&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
(which generates the static pages from Ghost)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; buster deploy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
(which uploads the static pages to Github)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, so good.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li class="footnote" id="fn:1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The days I spent trying to get Jekyll to play nice with my existing website! Arggggh. &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/welcome-to-ghost/#fnref:1" title="return to article"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>